99 8
1  إِذَا زُلْزِلَتِ الْأَرْضُ زِلْزَالَهَا  When the earth is shaken with its [final] earthquake
2  وَأَخْرَجَتِ الْأَرْضُ أَثْقَالَهَا  And the earth discharges its burdens
3  وَقَالَ الْإِنسَانُ مَا لَهَا  And man says, "What is [wrong] with it?" 
4  يَوْمَئِذٍ تُحَدِّثُ أَخْبَارَهَا  That Day, it will report its news
5  بِأَنَّ رَبَّكَ أَوْحَىٰ لَهَا  Because your Lord has commanded it.
6  يَوْمَئِذٍ يَصْدُرُ النَّاسُ أَشْتَاتًا لِّيُرَوْا أَعْمَالَهُمْ  That Day, the people will depart separated [into categories] to be shown [the result of] their deeds.
7  فَمَن يَعْمَلْ مِثْقَالَ ذَرَّةٍ خَيْرًا يَرَه  So whoever does an atom's weight of good will see it,
8  وَمَن يَعْمَلْ مِثْقَالَ ذَرَّةٍ شَرًّا يَرَهُ  And whoever does an atom's weight of evil will see it.
62 11
1  يُسَبِّحُ لِلَّهِ مَا فِي السَّمَاوَاتِ وَمَا فِي الْأَرْضِ الْمَلِكِ الْقُدُّوسِ الْعَزِيزِ الْحَكِيمِ  Whatever is in the heavens and whatever is on the earth is exalting Allah, the Sovereign, the Pure, the Exalted in Might, the Wise.
2  هُوَ الَّذِي بَعَثَ فِي الْأُمِّيِّينَ رَسُولًا مِّنْهُمْ يَتْلُو عَلَيْهِمْ آيَاتِهِ وَيُزَكِّيهِمْ وَيُعَلِّمُهُمُ الْكِتَابَ وَالْحِكْمَةَ وَإِن كَانُوا مِن قَبْلُ لَفِي ضَلَالٍ مُّبِينٍ  It is He who has sent among the unlettered a Messenger from themselves reciting to them His verses and purifying them and teaching them the Book and wisdom - although they were before in clear error -
3  وَآخَرِينَ مِنْهُمْ لَمَّا يَلْحَقُوا بِهِمْ ۚ وَهُوَ الْعَزِيزُ الْحَكِيمُ  And [to] others of them who have not yet joined them. And He is the Exalted in Might, the Wise.
4  ذَٰلِكَ فَضْلُ اللَّهِ يُؤْتِيهِ مَن يَشَاءُ ۚ وَاللَّهُ ذُو الْفَضْلِ الْعَظِيمِ  That is the bounty of Allah, which He gives to whom He wills, and Allah is the possessor of great bounty.
5  مَثَلُ الَّذِينَ حُمِّلُوا التَّوْرَاةَ ثُمَّ لَمْ يَحْمِلُوهَا كَمَثَلِ الْحِمَارِ يَحْمِلُ أَسْفَارًا ۚ بِئْسَ مَثَلُ الْقَوْمِ الَّذِينَ كَذَّبُوا بِآيَاتِ اللَّهِ ۚ وَاللَّهُ لَا يَهْدِي الْقَوْمَ الظَّالِمِينَ  The example of those who were entrusted with the Torah and then did not take it on is like that of a donkey who carries volumes [of books]. Wretched is the example of the people who deny the signs of Allah . And Allah does not guide the wrongdoing people.
6  قُلْ يَا أَيُّهَا الَّذِينَ هَادُوا إِن زَعَمْتُمْ أَنَّكُمْ أَوْلِيَاءُ لِلَّهِ مِن دُونِ النَّاسِ فَتَمَنَّوُا الْمَوْتَ إِن كُنتُمْ صَادِقِينَ  Say, "O you who are Jews, if you claim that you are allies of Allah, excluding the [other] people, then wish for death, if you should be truthful."
7  وَلَا يَتَمَنَّوْنَهُ أَبَدًا بِمَا قَدَّمَتْ أَيْدِيهِمْ ۚ وَاللَّهُ عَلِيمٌ بِالظَّالِمِينَ  But they will not wish for it, ever, because of what their hands have put forth. And Allah is Knowing of the wrongdoers.
8  قُلْ إِنَّ الْمَوْتَ الَّذِي تَفِرُّونَ مِنْهُ فَإِنَّهُ مُلَاقِيكُمْ ۖ ثُمَّ تُرَدُّونَ إِلَىٰ عَالِمِ الْغَيْبِ وَالشَّهَادَةِ فَيُنَبِّئُكُم بِمَا كُنتُمْ تَعْمَلُونَ  Say, "Indeed, the death from which you flee - indeed, it will meet you. Then you will be returned to the Knower of the unseen and the witnessed, and He will inform you about what you used to do."
9  يَا أَيُّهَا الَّذِينَ آمَنُوا إِذَا نُودِيَ لِلصَّلَاةِ مِن يَوْمِ الْجُمُعَةِ فَاسْعَوْا إِلَىٰ ذِكْرِ اللَّهِ وَذَرُوا الْبَيْعَ ۚ ذَٰلِكُمْ خَيْرٌ لَّكُمْ إِن كُنتُمْ تَعْلَمُونَ  you who have believed, when [the adhan] is called for the prayer on the day of Jumu'ah [Friday], then proceed to the remembrance of Allah and leave trade. That is better for you, if you only knew.
10  فَإِذَا قُضِيَتِ الصَّلَاةُ فَانتَشِرُوا فِي الْأَرْضِ وَابْتَغُوا مِن فَضْلِ اللَّهِ وَاذْكُرُوا اللَّهَ كَثِيرًا لَّعَلَّكُمْ تُفْلِحُونَ  And when the prayer has been concluded, disperse within the land and seek from the bounty of Allah, and remember Allah often that you may succeed.
11  وَإِذَا رَأَوْا تِجَارَةً أَوْ لَهْوًا انفَضُّوا إِلَيْهَا وَتَرَكُوكَ قَائِمًا ۚ قُلْ مَا عِندَ اللَّهِ خَيْرٌ مِّنَ اللَّهْوِ وَمِنَ التِّجَارَةِ ۚ وَاللَّهُ خَيْرُ الرَّازِقِينَ  But when they saw a transaction or a diversion, [O Muhammad], they rushed to it and left you standing. Say, "What is with Allah is better than diversion and than a transaction, and Allah is the best of providers."
93 11
1  وَالضُّحَىٰ  By the morning brightness
2  وَاللَّيْلِ إِذَا سَجَىٰ  And [by] the night when it covers with darkness,
3  مَا وَدَّعَكَ رَبُّكَ وَمَا قَلَىٰ  Your Lord has not taken leave of you, [O Muhammad], nor has He detested [you].
4  وَلَلْآخِرَةُ خَيْرٌ لَّكَ مِنَ الْأُولَىٰ  And the Hereafter is better for you than the first [life].
5  وَلَسَوْفَ يُعْطِيكَ رَبُّكَ فَتَرْضَىٰ  And your Lord is going to give you, and you will be satisfied.
6  أَلَمْ يَجِدْكَ يَتِيمًا فَآوَىٰ  Did He not find you an orphan and give [you] refuge?
7  وَوَجَدَكَ ضَالًّا فَهَدَىٰ  And He found you lost and guided [you],
8  وَوَجَدَكَ عَائِلًا فَأَغْنَىٰ  And He found you poor and made [you] self-sufficient.
9  فَأَمَّا الْيَتِيمَ فَلَا تَقْهَرْ  So as for the orphan, do not oppress [him].
10  وَأَمَّا السَّائِلَ فَلَا تَنْهَرْ  And as for the petitioner, do not repel [him].
11  وَأَمَّا بِنِعْمَةِ رَبِّكَ فَحَدِّثْ  But as for the favor of your Lord, report [it].
71 28
1  إِنَّا أَرْسَلْنَا نُوحًا إِلَىٰ قَوْمِهِ أَنْ أَنذِرْ قَوْمَكَ مِن قَبْلِ أَن يَأْتِيَهُمْ عَذَابٌ أَلِيمٌ  Indeed, We sent Noah to his people, [saying], "Warn your people before there comes to them a painful punishment."
2  قَالَ يَا قَوْمِ إِنِّي لَكُمْ نَذِيرٌ مُّبِينٌ  He said, "O my people, indeed I am to you a clear warner,
3  أَنِ اعْبُدُوا اللَّهَ وَاتَّقُوهُ وَأَطِيعُونِ  [Saying], 'Worship Allah, fear Him and obey me.
4  يَغْفِرْ لَكُم مِّن ذُنُوبِكُمْ وَيُؤَخِّرْكُمْ إِلَىٰ أَجَلٍ مُّسَمًّى ۚ إِنَّ أَجَلَ اللَّهِ إِذَا جَاءَ لَا يُؤَخَّرُ ۖ لَوْ كُنتُمْ تَعْلَمُونَ  Allah will forgive you of your sins and delay you for a specified term. Indeed, the time [set by] Allah, when it comes, will not be delayed, if you only knew.' " 
5  قَالَ رَبِّ إِنِّي دَعَوْتُ قَوْمِي لَيْلًا وَنَهَارًا  He said, "My Lord, indeed I invited my people [to truth] night and day.
6  فَلَمْ يَزِدْهُمْ دُعَائِي إِلَّا فِرَارًا  But my invitation increased them not except in flight.
7  وَإِنِّي كُلَّمَا دَعَوْتُهُمْ لِتَغْفِرَ لَهُمْ جَعَلُوا أَصَابِعَهُمْ فِي آذَانِهِمْ وَاسْتَغْشَوْا ثِيَابَهُمْ وَأَصَرُّوا وَاسْتَكْبَرُوا اسْتِكْبَارًا  And indeed, every time I invited them that You may forgive them, they put their fingers in their ears, covered themselves with their garments, persisted, and were arrogant with [great] arrogance.
8  ثُمَّ إِنِّي دَعَوْتُهُمْ جِهَارًا  Then I invited them publicly.
9  ثُمَّ إِنِّي أَعْلَنتُ لَهُمْ وَأَسْرَرْتُ لَهُمْ إِسْرَارًا  Then I announced to them and [also] confided to them secretly
10  فَقُلْتُ اسْتَغْفِرُوا رَبَّكُمْ إِنَّهُ كَانَ غَفَّارًا  And said, 'Ask forgiveness of your Lord. Indeed, He is ever a Perpetual Forgiver.
11  يُرْسِلِ السَّمَاءَ عَلَيْكُم مِّدْرَارًا  He will send [rain from] the sky upon you in [continuing] showers
12  وَيُمْدِدْكُم بِأَمْوَالٍ وَبَنِينَ وَيَجْعَل لَّكُمْ جَنَّاتٍ وَيَجْعَل لَّكُمْ أَنْهَارًا  And give you increase in wealth and children and provide for you gardens and provide for you rivers.
13  مَّا لَكُمْ لَا تَرْجُونَ لِلَّهِ وَقَارًا  What is [the matter] with you that you do not attribute to Allah [due] grandeur
14  وَقَدْ خَلَقَكُمْ أَطْوَارًا  While He has created you in stages?
15  أَلَمْ تَرَوْا كَيْفَ خَلَقَ اللَّهُ سَبْعَ سَمَاوَاتٍ طِبَاقًا  Do you not consider how Allah has created seven heavens in layers
16  وَجَعَلَ الْقَمَرَ فِيهِنَّ نُورًا وَجَعَلَ الشَّمْسَ سِرَاجًا  And made the moon therein a [reflected] light and made the sun a burning lamp?
17  وَاللَّهُ أَنبَتَكُم مِّنَ الْأَرْضِ نَبَاتًا  And Allah has caused you to grow from the earth a [progressive] growth.
18  ثُمَّ يُعِيدُكُمْ فِيهَا وَيُخْرِجُكُمْ إِخْرَاجًا  Then He will return you into it and extract you [another] extraction.
19  وَاللَّهُ جَعَلَ لَكُمُ الْأَرْضَ بِسَاطًا  And Allah has made for you the earth an expanse
20  لِّتَسْلُكُوا مِنْهَا سُبُلًا فِجَاجًا  That you may follow therein roads of passage.' "
21  قَالَ نُوحٌ رَّبِّ إِنَّهُمْ عَصَوْنِي وَاتَّبَعُوا مَن لَّمْ يَزِدْهُ مَالُهُ وَوَلَدُهُ إِلَّا خَسَارًا  Noah said, "My Lord, indeed they have disobeyed me and followed him whose wealth and children will not increase him except in loss.
22  وَمَكَرُوا مَكْرًا كُبَّارًا  And they conspired an immense conspiracy.
23  وَقَالُوا لَا تَذَرُنَّ آلِهَتَكُمْ وَلَا تَذَرُنَّ وَدًّا وَلَا سُوَاعًا وَلَا يَغُوثَ وَيَعُوقَ وَنَسْرًا  And said, 'Never leave your gods and never leave Wadd or Suwa' or Yaghuth and Ya'uq and Nasr.
24  وَقَدْ أَضَلُّوا كَثِيرًا ۖ وَلَا تَزِدِ الظَّالِمِينَ إِلَّا ضَلَالًا  And already they have misled many. And, [my Lord], do not increase the wrongdoers except in error."
25  مِّمَّا خَطِيئَاتِهِمْ أُغْرِقُوا فَأُدْخِلُوا نَارًا فَلَمْ يَجِدُوا لَهُم مِّن دُونِ اللَّهِ أَنصَارًا  Because of their sins they were drowned and put into the Fire, and they found not for themselves besides Allah [any] helpers.
26  وَقَالَ نُوحٌ رَّبِّ لَا تَذَرْ عَلَى الْأَرْضِ مِنَ الْكَافِرِينَ دَيَّارًا  And Noah said, "My Lord, do not leave upon the earth from among the disbelievers an inhabitant.
27  إِنَّكَ إِن تَذَرْهُمْ يُضِلُّوا عِبَادَكَ وَلَا يَلِدُوا إِلَّا فَاجِرًا كَفَّارًا  Indeed, if You leave them, they will mislead Your servants and not beget except [every] wicked one and [confirmed] disbeliever.
28  رَّبِّ اغْفِرْ لِي وَلِوَالِدَيَّ وَلِمَن دَخَلَ بَيْتِيَ مُؤْمِنًا وَلِلْمُؤْمِنِينَ وَالْمُؤْمِنَاتِ وَلَا تَزِدِ الظَّالِمِينَ إِلَّا تَبَارًا  My Lord, forgive me and my parents and whoever enters my house a believer and the believing men and believing women. And do not increase the wrongdoers except in destruction."